Lafayette mss., 1572-1939 LMC 2326
Lilly Library
Lafayette mss.
1572-1939
Lilly Library
Gardner, Walter P.
Lafayette, Marie Joseph Paul Yves Roch Gilbert Du Motier, marquis de, 1757-1834
Washington, George, 1732-1799
LMC 2326
5 folios oversize
21 Boxes 10 standard, 11 custom
The Lafayette mss., 1572-1939, consist of correspondence and papers assembled by banker Walter P. Gardner around the central figure of Marie Joseph Paul Yves Roch Gilbert du Motier, marquis de Lafayette, 1757-1834, general.
Conditions Governing Access
This collection is open for research.
Many collections are housed offsite; retrieval requires advance notice. Please make an appointment a minimum of one week in advance of your visit.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Gift: 1947
Biographical Note
Marie-Joseph Paul Yves Roch Gilbert du Motier, Marquis de La Fayette (1757-1834) was a French aristocrat and military officer. Lafayette (as he was known in the United States) played a key role in both the American Revolutionary War and the French Revolution.
Walter Pennett Gardner, 1869-1949, was a banker in Jersey City, New Jersey. Gardner served as judge of the New Jersey Court of Errors and Appeals before becoming president of the New Jersey Title Guarantee & Trust Co., the sixth largest bank in Jersey City during his tenure. For more biographical information on Gardner, see Scannell's New Jersey's First Citizens: Biographies and Portraits of the Notable Living Men and Women of New Jersey, with Informing Glimpses Into the State's History and Affairs, Volume 2, ed. John James Scannell and William Edgar Sackett, p. 177-178.
Scope and Contents
The collection includes personages preceding and following the life span of the Marquis de Lafayette as well as those of his contemporaries of the period of the American and French Revolutions. Among these are 8 members of the Albany Conference of 1754, 36 of the 56 Signers of the Declaration of Independence, 27 of the delegates to the Constitutional Convention of 1787, the Presidents of the United States from George Washington to Martin Van Buren and the rulers of England from Queen Anne to Queen Victoria, the rulers and France from Louis XIV to Louis Philippe, many of the outstanding figures of the Napoleonic Era and the Restoration period, and the members of the family of the Marquis de Lafayette.
The Lafayette household account book, 1814-1818, prepared by T. M. Pontonnier, which consists of forty leaves and is bound in modern red morroco, bears the approval signatures of General Lafayette and his son George Washington Lafayette with later appended dates of 1819, Jan. 1; May 18; and 1824, Jan. 30. The signature of W. P. Gardner on a fly leaf indicates the volume was formerly a part of the Gardner collection.
Most of the manuscripts are written either in English or French; four in Dutch (1674/5, Mar. 11; 1778, Mar. 29; 1790, Mar. 1; 1796, Aug. 19); seven in German (1749, Aug. 3; 1765, Jan. 5; 1785, Jan. 16; 1787, Jan. 28; 1808, Apr. 30; 1814, Apr. 1; 1824); one in Italian (1815, Dec. 4); five in Latin (1726, Mar. 26; 1726, Aug. 8; 1791; 1796, June 16; n.d. (Pius VII)); two in Russian (1790, June 10; 1808, Oct. 11).
The red wax seal of Lafayette bearing his cypher and surrounded by his motto "Cur Non" is found on the letter of the marquis de Lafayette to Bushrod Washington on 1825, Aug. 13 (see Jules Cloquet, Recollections of the private life of General Lafayette, London, printed for Baldwin and Cradock, 1835 (Lilly DC146 .L2 C6 p. 184).
The manuscripts were collected by Walter Pennett Gardner, 1869-1949, banker of Jersey City, New Jersey, and include correspondence with his contemporaries about several Lafayette items. They were acquired from Gardner for Indiana University by George Alexander Ball, 1862-1955, manufacturer of Muncie, Indiana, acting for the Ball Brothers Foundation in 1947.
The material originally was mounted in fifty loose-leaf volumes and arranged so as to interleave the texts of four printed works; John Frederick Schroeder, Life and Times of Washington; Charlemagne Tower, The Marquis de Lafayette in the American Revolution; Brand Whitlock, La Fayette; and August Levasseur, Lafayette in America in 1824 and 1825. The volumes, except for the two index volumes, have been dismantled, the manuscripts arranged chronologically, and the major portion of the printed illustrative material of pamphlets, broadsides and portraits distributed to be individually catalogued.
The two bound volumes of the index and the two notebook copies of the index remain with the manuscript collection.
Published sources for the Lafayette mss. include: Roger Montmort, Antoine Charles du Houx, baron de Viomenil, Baltimore, Johns Hopkins Press, 1935 (E265 .V76); Memoirs of Lafayette... Boston...E. G. House, 1824, pages 214-215 (DC146 .L2 M5); Jared Sparks, Life of Gouverneur Morris, Boston, Gray and Bowen, 1832, 3 vols. Vol. 1, pages 406-410 (E302.6 .M7 S7); Brand Whitlock, La Fayette, New York, D. Appleton, 1929, 2 vols., Vol. II, between pages 22-23, and page 246 (DC146 .L2 W6); W. E. Woodward, Lafayette, New York, Farrar and Rinehart, 1938, pages 155-6 (Lilly DC146 .L2 W8); Manuscripts, Vol. X, no. 2, Spring, 1958, page 14; The letters of Lafayette to Washington, 1777-1779, edited by Louis Gottschalk, privately printed by Helen Fahnestock Hubbard, New York, 1944 (E207 .W2 W18); Lafayette Letters in the Bostonian Society, edited by Horace Henry Morse, Bostonian Society Publications, 2nd Series, Vol. IV, 1924 (F73.1 .B8, 2d series, v. 4); Lafayette in Virginia, unpublished letters from the original manuscripts in the Virginia State Library and the Library of Congress, Baltimore, the Johns Hopkins Press, 1928 (E237 .L16); Lida Rose McCabe, Ardent Adrienne, New York, D. Appleton, 1930, pages 296-298 (Indiana State Library, call no. 923 .L1611mc); Jules Cloquet, Recollections of the private life of General Lafayette, London, printed for Baldwin and Cradock, 1835 (Lilly DC146 .L2 C6, pages 294-295).
Printed matter includes the following: an envelope of commemorative postage stamps; two boxes of facsimile and printed correspondence not catalogued, arranged chronologically, 1067-1936; one folio container of oversize facsimile-printed correspondence, not catalogued material; five boxes of pictures; four boxes of miscellaneous printed items; one folio container of oversize picture and printed material; one box of Marquis de Lafayette printed and pictorial material; one box of Gardner memorabilia; four boxes of Schroeder's Washington; two boxes of Tower's Lafayette; one box of Whitlock's La Fayette; one box of Lavasseur's Lafayette in America.
The original of the Lafayette letter to Friedrich List, July 13, 1824, which had arrived as a photocopy with the collection assembled by Gardner was acquired in November 1972 from International Autographs, New York.
Arrangement
The collection is arranged into the following series: Manuscripts, Facsimile & Printed, Portraits, and Memorabilia.
Related Materials
See Lafayette mss. II, Lafayette mss. III, Lafayette mss. IV, and Gottschalk mss., also located at the Lilly Library, Indiana University, Bloomington, Indiana.
United States--History--Revolution, 1775-1783; France -- History -- Revolution, 1789-1799
- Manuscripts
  - Chronological
    - A list of twelve men, pensioners, selected by the King to insure the safety of the Bastille, 1572, April 1 (Ovflat 30)
      Scope and Contents
      "The Ancient Bastille - A list of twelve men, pensioners, made up by the King to insure the safety of the Bastille."
    - Lafayette of the 16th Century, 1582; ALS 2 p. (Box 1, Folder 1)
      Includes typed heading from scrapbook page
    - De La Tremoille writes from London to the Prince of Orange, Frederic Henry (1625-1647), 1641, May 4; ALS 2 p. (includes seal) (Box 1, Folder 1)
      Referring to some insult or offense to the writer
      Also includes typescript
    - Warwicke - Prize papers for the ships "Flushing" and "Sampson" taken by the Irish Squadron, 1646, September 3; ALS 2 p. (Box 1, Folder 1)
    - Theophilus Suffolke at Suffolke House, 1639, December 7; ALS (Box 1, Folder 1)
    - Jo. Hammer - Old English, 1590; ALS (Box 1, Folder 1)
    - Earl of Arlington at Whitehall, 1666, November 3; ALS (Box 1, Folder 1)
      Letter is torn and pasted on scrapbook page with an engraving of Bennet, Earl of Arlington
    - Rob Long - On money matters, 1666, May; ALS (Box 1, Folder 1)
      On verso of "1666, November 3 - Earl of Arlington"
    - Sir Stephen Fox - Warrant for pay of "Souldiers and for fire and candles", 1669, March; Printed document signed with autograph fill-ins and note on verso (Box 1, Folder 1)
    - Anne Marie Louise Orleans, niece of Louis XIII, 1671 (Ovflat 30)
      "Anne Marie Louise d'Orleans, Duchesse de Montpensier - 1627-1693. 'La Grande Mademoiselle' - daughter of Gaston d'Orleans, brother of Louis XIII."
    - Evert Wendell - Mortgage to Johannis Wendell on property in New York City, 1674, March 11; ALS (Box 1, Folder 1)
      "The Wendells are one of the oldest Dutch families in New York City."
      Includes typed heading and note from scrapbook page
      Evert Jansen Wendell came from Embden, East Friesland, Holland, in 1640 to Beverwyck, the site of Fort Orange, now Albany, N.Y. with his wife Susanna du Trieux, son Johannis and Johannis' wife, Elizabeth Stacto.
    - Dancing Master presents his bill for lessons to the Dauphin and his wife, 1686, July 2; ALS (Box 1, Folder 1)
    - Louis XIV and Colbert (seal), 1687, June 12 (Ovflat 30)
      Includes typed translation into English
    - Samuel Sewall and Edro Bromfield, Justices of the Peace - Commitment papers for a woman taken with stolen goods. "Remnants of serge stuff and blew linen.", 1692/3, January 28; ALS with two seals (Box 1, Folder 1)
      "The document was written in the year of the Witch Trials in Salem and Sewall was one of the Judges."
    - "William R." (William III), also signed by Hampden and by Seymour - Payment to "Our Right Trusty and Rt. Welbeloved Cousin Daniel, Earl of Nottingham our Principal Secretary of State - for extraordinary affaires which improve Our Service.", 1692, March 4; ALS (Box 1, Folder 1)
    - Louis Antoine, Archbishop de Paris (Cardinal de Noailles, a great grandfather of Madame de la Lafayette) to "Monseigneur" - The sad news of the death of Madame la Comtesse d'Auvergne, 1698, November 3; ALS 2 p. (Box 1, Folder 1)
    - John Quick to his son-in-law, Rev. Mr. Benjamin Coleman, "Minister of the Gospel at Boston in New England", 1701, July 11; ALS on scrapbook page (Box 1, Folder 2)
      "A God-Fearing Briton, in 1701, to his son-in-law, a minister in Boston. The transcript on the verso is by the courtesy of Rev. Albert von Schlieder, D. D. of Hackensack, NJ. He tells me that one word in line 9 of the original is probably obsolete. One of the ailments mentioned near the end of the letter is difficult to decipher, perhaps it is "strangling."
      Includes typed heading and note on scrapbook page
      Also includes transcript by Rev. Albert von Schlieder on General Synod of the Reformed Church in America stationery
    - Godolphin - Order for payment to Juliana, Countess of Burlington, of £250 for quarter year allowance as one of the "Ladys of the Bed Chamber of Her Majesty", 1703, January 15; ALS (Box 1, Folder 2)
    - Madame de Maintenon (Francoise d'Aubigne) - Referring to the Order of Carmelites, 1708, May 8; ALS (Box 1, Folder 2)
    - Godolphin - Money order, 1709, July 29; ALS (on printed Order) (Box 1, Folder 2)
    - "An Act for the Raising £5,000 for Payment of Province Debts for Subsistence and Wages of Soldiers" (Dummer's War)., 1709, October 6; ALS (Box 1, Folder 2)
    - De Riemer, "Fourman of the Grand Jury" - a True Bill for Breach of the Peace in the house of Capt. Dohonidur, 1713, May 5; ALS on scrapbook page (Box 1, Folder 2)
    - "Anne R." (Queen Anne), also signed by Lord Bolingbroke - Order for Thomas, Lord Arch-Bishop of Canterbury to direct that Church Wardens call at the homes of each Parish "To collect the benevolences of charitable and well disposed persons to relieve the poorer sort of our Subjects in and about the City of London who do suffer great hardships at this time", 1713, December 21; ALS (Box 1, Folder 2)
    - A Writ of the Court of Common Pleas, Charleston, SC - "Wee streightly command you" - in the matter of an estate of which a Ralph Izard was Executor, 1714, October 19; ALS with seal (Box 1, Folder 2)
    - d'Aumale to Compte Bailly - "Madame de Maintenon bears up bravely in spite of the deepest grief which she has met with steadfast courage and admirable resignation [at the death of Louis XIV]", 1715, September 13; ALS 2 p. with seal (Box 1, Folder 2)
    - Philippe d'Orleans (Regent, Sept. 1, 1715), Au Buen Retiro - He asks that in the next distribution of benefits, the Abbey of Moissac be given to a certain Abbe, 1715, November 24; ALS (Box 1, Folder 2)
      "NOTE: Louis XV did not assume the duties of the Throne until the death of the Regent, Phillipe d'Orleans in 1723."
    - Robert Harley, Earl of Oxford, 1716, May 31; ALS (Box 1, Folder 2)
    - Writ of the Mayor's Court, City of New York - signed by Joseph Murray, 1718, September 23; ALS (Box 1, Folder 2)
    - Philippe d'Orleans (Regent of France) to his "Dear Cousin" - Social note, 1719, March 1; ALS 2 p. (Box 1, Folder 2)
      Includes typed translation into English "NOTE: Louis XV did not assume the duties of the Throne until the death of the Regent, Phillipe d'Orleans in 1723."
    - Chancellor d'Aguesseau (great grandfather of Madame La Fayette) to de Soissons, 1719, June; ALS 2 p. (Box 1, Folder 2)
    - Lords Walpole, Doddington and Oxenden at Whitehall - Pay warrant for "Latin Secretary", 1728, May 21; ALS (Box 1, Folder 2)
      Includes hand-colored engraving pasted on verso
    - Dormt Warrt - William Lee of Latinsary 20th ??, [unknown date]; AL (Box 1, Folder 2)
    - Inventory signed by Caleb Cooman?, 1703, December 20; ALS (Box 1, Folder 2)
    - Writ of Possession "Inferiour Court of Common Pleas," County of Suffolk, MA. Suit for one half of Wind Mill property at Roxbury Neck and equipment. Signed by John Ballantine and endorsed "satisfied" by Sheriff Dudley, 1720, September 16; ALS 2 p. (Box 1, Folder 3)
    - William Burnett, Captain General and Governor in Chief of the Province of New York - Letters of Administration, estate of Peter de Wit, 1721, November 7; ALS on scrapbook page (Box 1, Folder 3)
    - William Augustus, Duke of Cumberland, 1725, March 1 (Ovflat 30)
    - Debenture of Samuel Clark, 1726, March 26; AD (Box 1, Folder 3)
      related to George I somehow?
    - "Georgius R." (George I), Kensington - Notification to Francis, Archbishop of Mayence ("Kinsman and Dearest Friend") of the death at Vienna, July 27 of "our dearest Brother Maximilian, Duke of Brunswick and Luneberg", 1726, August; ADS (Box 1, Folder 3)
      Also includes typed translation into English
    - L. A. de Bourbon (Duc du Maine, son of Louis XIV and Madame de Montespan) to Cardinal de Fleury - Asks his Eminence to separately tell him and his brother of their fate and refers to a "crisis", 1727, April 6; ADS with seal 2 p. (Box 1, Folder 3)
    - Jonathan Read, a lawyer in Salem, MA - Briefs his reasons for appealing his case to the Supreme Court, 1728, September 18; ADS on scrapbook page (Box 1, Folder 3)
    - Signature of Queen Caroline of Ansbach, 1728; Autograph cut from letter (Box 1, Folder 3)
    - Promissory Note for £5.10, signed by Maccoy and acknowledged before John Chandler, Justice of the Peace, 1730, March 31; ADS (Box 1, Folder 3)
    - Cardinal de Rohan to the Minister of State, at Versailles - "the Officers who are concerned with the administration of the laws of Alsace should be instructed to pay regard to the old customs", 1730, January 16; ADS (Box 1, Folder 3)
      Includes typed explanation of contents in English
      "This letter of January 16, 1730, is to the Controller-General, Minister of State, and suggests that those officers who are concerned with the administration of the Laws in Alsace be instructed to pay regard to the old customs and to take different precautions from those to be taken in the other French provinces. De Rohan bases his judgment upon that of "a wise man" who has written him to that effect."
    - Duc de Noailles (grandfather of Madame Lafayette) to M. Gerault, at Paris - social note, 1732, October 4; ADS (Box 1, Folder 3)
    - Robert Lurting, New York City - Writ of Mayor's Court - special bail, 1733, May 7; ADS (Box 1, Folder 3)
      "Robert Lurting was one of the first wardens of Trinity Church, New York City in 1697"
    - Phelippeux Maurepas to M. Ayrouiere, at Versailles - Regarding the plan of the Port of Antibes, 1733, May 14; ADS on scrapbook page (Box 1, Folder 3)
      "Jean Frederic Phhelippeux Maurepas (1701-1781) displeased the all-powerful Pompadour and was banished from court in 1740. Louis XVI recalled him and made him Prime Minister 1774."
    - Land Deed signed by Joseph Rawlings in New Hampshire, 1733, October 5; ADS on scrapbook page (Box 1, Folder 3)
    - George Clarke, Colonial Governor of New York - Appointment of Administrators for Estate of John Cook, 1734, January 20; ADS (Box 1, Folder 3)
      "These Letters of Administration were signed in 1734 by George Clarke. During the reign of Queen Anne he came to America to mend his fortunes, he was appointed to the Council and soon ranked next to Van Dam. On the death of Governor Crosby, Van Dam should have succeeded, but Clarke had more influence with his fellows and was proclaimed Governor pro tem by the Council, and the British Home Office commissioned him. His Administration was a fairly wise and successful one. Clarke died in 1763."
    - A private letter in which is described by an eye witness the wedding of Anne, daughter of George II, the dresses, jewels, music and supper, and the undressing of the bride and of the groom (the Prince of Orange). The writer tells how the King went to see the Princess in bed and the Prince of Wales brought in the Prince of Orange who got into the bed before them all. The couple sat up in bed whereupon the doors were opened for all the Peers and Peeresses to go in, 1734, April 3; ADS (Box 1, Folder 3)
      "A highly interesting letter from a lady who was present at the marriage ceremony of Anne, daughter of George II. It is her description of the event and gives the gossip in the court circles about it."
    - Personal letter by Madame de Sabran, 1735, February 23; ADS 2 p. (Box 1, Folder 3)
    - Sight draft signed by John Penn, 1735, August 11; ADS on scrapbook page (Box 1, Folder 3)
      "John Penn was born in Philadelphia in 1700, the eldest son of William Penn and his second wife. He went to England in 1735 and died there without issue in 1746. He is known as the "American Penn" and is the only one of the family in the direct male line who remained a Quaker."
    - Jonathan Trumble to James Pitts at Boston - about a consignment of beef and pork, 1738, November 27; ADS 2 p. (Box 1, Folder 3)
      "NOTE - Later, the Trumble family spelled their name Trumbull."
    - Robert Auchmuty - Legal paper, 1739; ADS (Box 1, Folder 3)
      "The first Auchmuty in America"
    - Sir William Fairfax in King George County, VA - Order for official survey of ungranted lands, 1740, February 26; ADS (Box 1, Folder 4)
      "Sir William Fairfax, whose daughter Anne married Lawrence Washington, General Washington's elder brother, was the cousin of Thomas, the sixth Baron Fairfax. He came to America to manage his cousin's vast estate in northern Virginia and the Shenandoah Valley consisting of about five million acres. This took in twenty one counties comprising nearly one quarter of the Commonwealth of Virginia. It was Thomas, Lord Fairfax, who emplored George Washington, the young surveyor, to map his lands west of the Blue Ridge. Sir Thomas lived on his estate, at Greenway Court, as a bachelor and died there in 1782. Sir William Fairfax had a beautiful home called Belvoir and George Washington was a frequent and welcome visitor there."
    - Judgment writ to Sheriff - Windham, Connecticut, 1740/1, February 28; Printed document with autograph fill-ins (Box 1, Folder 4)
      "Ebenezer Gray was one of the well-known family of Connecticut. Thomas Dyar, the attorney who endorsed this paper, was a celebrated Indian fighter."
    - Richard Waldron, at Charlestown - giving early news of the repulse of Admiral Vernon at Cartagena (South America), 1741, June 27; ADS with seal (Box 1, Folder 4)
    - Samuel Sherburne and Henry Sherburne - portion of deed, 1741, September 15; ADS on scrapbook page (Box 1, Folder 4)
    - Henri Francois Daguesseau (great grandfather of Madame Lafayette) to M. de Roche - Concerning a Commission for Genest, 1743, May 26; ADS (Box 1, Folder 4)
      Includes typed heading on scrapbook page
    - Cardinal d'Auvergne to Cardinal Passionei - Concerning the King's architect and certain ceremonies in the Cathedral, 1743, September 11; ADS on scrapbook page (Box 1, Folder 4)
    - George R. (George II), also signed by Sir Henry Pelham, Lord Middlesex and Lord Lytelton - Warrant for payment to Duke of Montagu and his Regiment of Foot - "we have fit to allow this in consideration of a Rebellion being now in the Kingdom", 1745, March 10; ADS 2 p. (Box 1, Folder 4)
    - John Stover to Ebenezer Stover, at Boston - telling of the arrival of news from England that Sir William Pepperell has been confirmed as General and that Sir Peter Warren is made "Rear Admiral of the Blew" and Governor of Louisbourg - two regiments are coming from Gibraltar, 1745, September 27; ADS (Box 1, Folder 4)
      "The 'Warren' incidentally mentioned is Sir Peter Warren, British Admiral who later married a daughter of Stephen de Lancey of New York, bought a large estate in the Mohawk Valley and placed it in charge of his nephew, William, afterwards Sir William Johnson."
      "A neighbor writes from Louisbourg to his family in Boston telling them that happy news is come from England that General Pepperrell has been knighted for his victory over the French."
    - William Gowen (his mark) to Nathan Bartlet - Deed to land in Kittery, 1746, May 27; ADS on scrapbook page (Box 1, Folder 4)
    - Comte de Argenson, War Minister to Louis XV - on military matters, 1747, August 4; ADS (Box 1, Folder 4)
    - John Rattray and John Lining, in SC - Petition for Writ of Attachment, 1747, November 6; ADS (Box 1, Folder 4)
    - Governor William Shirley to Rt. Hon. William Pitt - Warrant for payment of £150 to men of "late Regiment commanded by Col. Waldo", 1747, December 17; ADS (Box 1, Folder 4)
      "Payment of the troops in the Louisburg campaign"
    - Governor William Shirley to Rt. Hon. William Pitt - Bill of Exchange for £300 sterling "for payment of troops in late intended invasion of Canada", 1747, December 27; ADS (Box 1, Folder 4)
      "Governor Shirley draws on Right Honorable William Pitt for the payment of the army in the Canadian Expedition"
    - Governor William Shirley to Governor Wentworth of New Hampshire - Advising him of a meeting at Middletown, Conn. of the Commissioners of Massachusetts, Connecticut, and New York, to resume the discussion that was before a meeting recently held in New York, for the making of some "representations to His Majesty concerning the good of the cause", 1747, December 28; ADS (Box 1, Folder 4)
      "Governor Shirley of Massachusetts writes to Governor Wentworth of New Hampshire regarding an interstate convention, indicating that as early as 1747 the colonies were cooperating. Undoubtedly these meetings laid the foundation for the Albany Congress of 1754, fathered by Benjamin Franklin."